PROFESSOR: So I'm going
to begin by trying
to build some intuition for how
one might be able to do staging
from cross-sectional
data, and we'll
return to this question of
combined staging subtyping only
much later.
So imagine that we had data
that lived in one dimension.
Here, each data point
is an individual,
we observe their data at
just one point in time,
and suppose we knew exactly
which biomarker to look at.
Right?
So I gave you an
example of that here,
when you might look at some
antibody expression level,
and that might be what
I call biomarker A,
is if you knew exactly
what biomarker to look at,
you might just put each
person along this line
and you might conjecture that
maybe on one side of the line,
this is the early disease, and
that the other sort of line,
maybe that's the late disease.
Why might that be a
reasonable conjecture?
What would be an
alternative conjecture?
Why don't you talk
to your neighbors
and see if you guys
can come up with
some alternative conjectures.
Let's go.
All right, that's enough.
So hopefully simple
questions, so I
won't give you too much time.
All right, so what would
be another conjecture?
So again, our goal is we have
one observation per individual,
each individual is in some
unknown stage of the disease,
we would like to be able to
sort individuals and turn it
into early and late
stages of the disease.
I give you one conjecture
of how to do that, sorting,
what would be another
reasonable conjecture?
Raise your hand.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: That there's
the different--
that they have different
types of the same diseases.
They all have the same
disease and it could--
just one of the subtypes
might be sort of the--
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
So you're going back to the
example I gave here where you
could conflate these things.
I want to stick with
a simpler story,
let's suppose there's only
one subtype of the disease.
What would be another way
to sort the patients given
this data where the data is
these points that you see here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: For any disease in
the middle range, and then
as you [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: OK, so
maybe early disease
is right over here, and when
things get bad, the patient--
this biomarker starts
to become abnormal,
and abnormality,
for whatever reason,
might be sort of to the
right or to the left.
Now I think that is a
conjecture one could have.
I would argue that
that's perhaps
not a very natural
conjecture given
what we know about common
biomarkers that are measured
from the human body
and the way that they
respond to disease progression.
Unless you're in the situation
of having multiple disease
subtypes where, for example,
going to the right marker
might correspond to
one disease subtype
and going to the left
marker might correspond
to another disease subtype.
What would be
another conjecture?
You guys are missing
the easy one.
Yeah, in the back.
AUDIENCE: Well, it
might just be one
where the high values
are [INAUDIBLE] stage
and low values are later ones?
PROFESSOR: Exactly.
So this might be early disease
and that might be late disease.
AUDIENCE: It says vice
versa on this slide.
PROFESSOR: Oh, does it really?
Oh shoot.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Right, right, OK, OK.
Thank you.
Next time I'll take out
that lower vice versa.
[LAUGHTER]
That's why you guys
aren't saying that.
OK.
OK, so this is good.
Now I think we're
all on the same page,
and we had some idea of what
are some of the assumptions
that one might need
to make in order
to actually do anything here.
Like for example,
we are making some--
we'll probably have to make some
assumption about continuity,
that there might be some gradual
progression of the biomarker
relevance from early to late,
and it might be getting larger,
it might be getting smaller.
If it's indeed the scenario that
we talked about earlier where
we said like early
disease might be here
and late disease might be going
to either side, in that case,
I think one could easily argue
that with just information
we have here, disease
progression-- disease stage
is unidentifiable, right?
Because you wouldn't
know where would it--
where should you-- where should
that transition point be?
So here, here, here,
here, here, here.
In fact, the same
problem arises here.
Like you don't know,
is it early disease--
is it going this way or
is it going that way?
What would be one way to
try to disentangle this just
to try to get us all on
the same page, right?
So suppose it was only
going this direction
or going that
direction, how could we
figure out which is which?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Maybe we had data
on low key and other data
about how much time we had taken
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
No, that's great.
So maybe we have data on
let's say death information,
or even just age.
And if we started from a
very, very rough assumption
that disease stage let's say
grows monotonically with age,
then--
and if you had made an
additional assumption
that the disease stages are--
that the people
who are coming in
are uniformly drawn from across
disease stages, with those two
assumptions alone, then you
could, for example, look
at the average age of
individuals over here
and the average age of
individuals over here,
and you'd say, the one
with the larger average age
is the late disease one.
Or you could look at time to
death if you had for each--
for each data
point you also knew
how long until that
individual died,
you could look at
average time to death
for these individuals
versus those individuals
and try to tease it
apart in that way.
That's what you meant.
OK, so I'm just trying to give
you some intuition for how
this might be possible.
What about if your
data looked like this?
So now you have two biomarkers.
So we've only gone up
by one dimension only,
and we want to figure out
where's early, where's late?
Already starts to become
more challenging, right?
So the intuition that
I want you to have
is that we're going
to have to make
some assumptions about
disease progression,
such as the ones we
were just discussing,
and we also have to
get lucky in some way.
So for example, one
way of getting lucky
would be to have a
real lot of data.
So if you had a
ton, ton of data,
and you made an additional
assumption that your data lives
in some low dimensional manifold
where on one side of manifold
is early disease and the
other side of manifold
is late disease,
then you might be
able to discover that
manifold from this data,
and you might conjecture that
the manifold is something
like that, that trajectory
that I'm outlining there
with my hand.
But for you to be able
to do that, of course,
you need to have
enough data, all right?
So it's going to be now
a trade-off between just
having cross-sectional
data, it might be OK so long
as you have a real
lot of that data
so you can sort of
fill in the spaces
and really identify
that manifold.
A different approach
might be, well maybe you
don't have just pure
cross-sectional data,
maybe you have two or
maybe three samples
from each patient.
And then you can
color code this.
So you might say, OK,
green is patient 1--
or patient A, we'll call it,
and this is the first time
point from patient A, second
time point from patient A,
third and fourth time
points from patient A. Red
is patient B, and you have
two time points for patient B,
and blue here is
patient C, and you
have 1, 2, 3 time points
from patient C. OK?
Now again, it's not
very dense data,
we can't really draw
curves out, But now
we can start to get a
sense of the ordering.
And again, now we can-- even
though we don't-- we're not
in a dense setting like
we were here, here,
we'd still nonetheless be able
to figure out that probably
the manifold looks a little
bit like this, right?
And so again, I'm just
trying to build intuition
around when disease
progression modeling
for cross-sectional
data might be possible,
but this is a wide open field.
And so today, I'll
be telling you
about a few algorithms
that try to build
on some of these intuitions
for doing disease progression
modeling, but they will
break down very, very easily.
They'll break down
when these assumptions
I gave you don't hold,
they'll break down
when your data is
high dimensional,
they'll break down
when your data looks
like this where you don't
just have a single subtype
of perhaps a multiple subtypes.
and so this is a really very
active area of research,
and it's an area that I think
we can make a lot of progress
on in the field in the
next several years.
So I'll begin with one case
study coming from my own work
where we developed an
algorithm for learning
from cross-sectional
data, and we valued it
in the context of chronic
obstructive pulmonary disorder
or COPD.
COPD is a condition of
the lungs typically caused
by air pollution or smoking,
and it has a reasonably good
staging mechanism.
One uses what's called a
spirometry device in order
to measure the lung function
of individual at any one point
in time.
So for example, you take
this spirometry device,
you stick it in your
mouth, and you breathe in,
and then you exhale,
and one measure
is how long it takes in
order to exhale all your air,
and that is going to
be a measure of how
good your lungs are.
And so then one can take
that measure of your function
and one can stage how
severe the person's COPD is,
and that goes by what's
called the gold criteria.
So for example, in
stage 1 of the COPD,
common treatments
involve just vaccinations
using a short-acting
bronchodilator only when
needed.
When the disease stage gets
much more severe, like stage 4,
than often treatment
is recommended
to be inhaling
glucocorticosteroids
if there are repeated
aspirations of the disease,
long-term oxygen If respiratory
failure occurs, and so on.
And so this is a disease that's
reasonably well-understood
because there exists a
good staging mechanism.
And I would argue
that when we want
to understand how to
do disease staging
in a data-driven
fashion, we should first
start by working with
either synthetic data,
or we should start with
working with a disease where
we have some idea of what the
actual true disease staging is.
And that way, we can look to
see what our algorithms would
recover in those
scenarios, and does
it align with what
we would expect
either from the way
the data was generated
or from the existing
medical literature.
And that's why we chose COPD.
Because it is
well-understood, and there's
a wealth of literature
on it, and because we
have data on it which is much
messier than the type of data
that went into the original
studies, and we could ask,
could we come to
the same conclusions
as those original studies?
So in this work, we're
going to use data
from the electronic
medical record.
We're only going to look
at a subset of the EMR,
in particular,
diagnosis codes that
are recorded for a patient
at any point in time,
and we're going to assume
that we do not have access
to spirometry data at all.
So we don't have any obvious
way of staging the patient's
disease.
The general approach
is going to be
to build a generative model
for disease progression.
At a very high level,
this is a Markov model.
It's a model that specifies the
distribution of the patient's
data, which is shown
here in the bottom,
as it evolves over time.
According to a number
of hidden variables
that are shown in the top,
these S variables that
denote disease stages, and
these X variables that denote
comorbidities that
the patient might
have at that point in time,
these X and S variables
are always assumed
to the unobserved.
So if you were to clump them
together into one variable,
this would look exactly
like a hidden Markov model.
And moreover, we're
not going to assume
that we have a lot
of longitudinal data
for a patient.
In particular, COPD evolves over
a 10 to 20 years, and the data
that we'll be learning from
here has data only over one
to three-year time range.
The challenge will be, can
we take data in this one
to three-year time range and
somehow stitch it together
across large numbers
of patients to get
a picture of what the 20-year
progression of the disease
might look like?
The way that we're
going to do that
is by learning the parameters
of this probabilistic model.
And then from the
parameters, we're
going to either infer the
patient's actual disease stage
and thus sort them, or
actually simulate data
from this model to see what
a 20-year trajectory might
look like.
Is the goal clear?
All right.
So now what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to step into
this model piece
by piece to tell you what
each of these components
are, and I'll start out with a
very topmost piece shown here
by the red box.
So this is the model of the
patient's disease progression
at any one point in time.
So this variable,
S1, for example,
might denote the patient's
disease stage on March 2011;
S2 might denote the patient's
disease stage April 2011;
S capital T might denote
the patient's disease stage
June 2012.
So we're going to have
one random variable
for each observation of the
patient's data that we have.
And notice that the observations
of the patient's data
might be at very
irregular time intervals,
and that's going to be OK
with this approach, OK?
So notice that there is a
one-month gap between S1
and S2, but a four-month gap
between St minus 1 and St, OK?
So we're going to model
the patient's disease stage
at the point in
time when we have
an observation for the patient.
S denotes a discrete
disease stage in this model.
So S might be a value from
1 up to 4, maybe 1 up to 10
where 1 is denoting a early
disease stage and 4 or 10
might denote a much
later disease stage.
If we have a sequence of
observations per patient--
for example, we might have
an observation on March
and then in April, we're
going to denote the disease
stage by S1 and S2, what this
model is going to talk about
is the probability distribution
of transitioning from whatever
the disease stage
at S1 is to whatever
the disease stage at S2.
Now because the time
interval is between stages
are not homogeneous, we have to
have a transition distribution
that takes into
consideration that time gap.
And to do that, we use what's
known as a continuous time
Markov process.
Formally, we say that the
transition distribution--
so the probability of
transitioning from stage I
at time t minus 1 to
state j at time t,
given as input the difference
in time intervals--
the difference in
time points delta--
so delta is the number of months
between the two observations.
So this conditional
distribution is
going to be given by the
matrix exponential of this time
interval times a matrix Q.
And then here, the matrix
Q gives us the parameters
that we want to learn.
So let me contrast
this to things
that you might
already be used to.
In a typical hidden
Markov model,
you might have
asked t goes to St--
or St minus 1 goes to St,
and you might imagine just
parametrizing St given St
minus 1 just by a lookup table.
So for example, if
the number of states--
for each running variable is
3, then you would have a 3
by 3 table where for
each state St minus 1,
you have some
probability of transition
to the corresponding state
St, so this might be something
like 0.9, 0.9,
0.9, where notice,
I'm having a very large
value along the diagonal,
because if, let's say,
a very small period--
so a priori, we might
believe that patients
stay in the same
disease, and then
one might imagine
that the probably
transitioning from state
1 at time t minus 1
to state 2 at time t might
be something like 0.09,
and the probability of skipping
state 2, going directly
to state 3 from state
1 might be something
much smaller like 0.01, OK?
And we might say something
like that the probability--
we might imagine
that the probability
of going in a
backwards direction,
going from stage 2
at time t minus 1
to let's say stage 1 at time
t, that might be 0 all right?
So you might imagine that
actually this is the model,
and what that's saying is
something like you never
go in the backwards
direction, and you're
more likely to
transition to the state
immediately adjacent
to the current stage
and very unlikely
to skip a stage.
So this would be
an example of how
you would parametrize the
transition distribution
in a typical discrete
time Markov model,
and the story here is going
to be different specifically
because we don't know
the time intervals.
So intuitively, if a lot of
time has passed between the two
observations, then we want
to allow for an accelerated
process.
We want to allow for
the fact that you
might want to skip many
different stages to go
to your next time step, to go
to the stage of the next time
step, because so
much time has passed.
And that intuitively is what
this scaling of this matrix
Q by delta corresponds to.
So the number of parameters
in this parameterization
is actually identical to
the number of parameters
in this parametrization, right?
So you have a matrix Q which
is given to you in essence
by the number of
states squared--
really, the number of states--
there's an additional
redundancy there
because it has to sum up to
1, but that's irrelevant.
And so the same
story here, but we're
going to now
parametrize the process
by in some sense the
infinitesimally small time
probability of transitioning.
So if you were to take the
derivative of this transition
distribution as the
time interval shrinks,
and then you were to integrate
over the time interval that
was observed and the probability
of transitioning from any state
to any other state with
that infinitesimally small
probability transitioning,
what you get out
is exactly this form.
And I'll leave-- this paper
is in the optional readings
for today's lecture, and
you can read through it
to get more intuition about the
continuous time Markov process.
Any questions so far?
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Those Q are the
same for both versions or--
PROFESSOR: Yes.
And this model Q is essentially
the same for all patients.
And you might imagine, if there
were disease subtypes, which
there aren't in this
approach, that Q might
be different for each subtype.
For example, you might
transition between stages
much more quickly for some
subtypes than for others.
Other questions?
Yep?
AUDIENCE: So-- OK, so
Q you said had like--
it's just like a screen
number used beforehand you
kind of like specified
these stages that you pick
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Correct.
Yes.
So you pre-specify the number of
stages that you want to model,
and there are many ways to
try to choose that parameter.
For example, you could look
at how about likelihood
under this model,
which is learned
for the different of stages.
You could use typical
model selection techniques
from machine learning
as another approach
where you try to penalize
complexity in some way.
Or, what we found here, because
of some of the other things
that I'm about to tell
you, it doesn't actually
matter that much.
So similarly to when one does
hard [INAUDIBLE] clustering
or even K-means clustering
or even learning
a problematic
topic model, if you
use a very small number of
topics or number of clusters,
you tend to learn very
coarse-grained topics
or clusters.
If you use very many more--
if you use a much
larger number of topics,
you tend to learn much
more fine-grained topics.
Same story is going
to happen here.
If you use a small
number of disease stages,
you're going to learn very
coarse-grained notions
of disease stages; if you
use more disease stages,
you're going to learn
a fine-grained notion;
but the overall
sorting of the patients
is going to end up
being very similar.
But to make that
statement, we're
going to need to make some
additional assumptions, which
I'm going to show
you in a few minutes.
Any other questions?
These are great questions.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: So do we know
the staging of the disease
because I
PROFESSOR: No, and
that's critical here.
So I'm assuming that these
variables-- these S's are all
hidden variables here.
And the way that we're
going to learn this model
is by maximum
likelihood estimation
where we marginalize over
the hidden variables,
just like you would do
in any EM type algorithm.
Any other questions?
All right, so what
I've just shown
you is the topmost
part of the model,
now I'm going to talk
about a horizontal slice.
So I'm going to talk about
one of these time points.
So if you were to look
at the translation--
the rotation of one of
those time points, what you
would get out is this model.
These X's are also
hidden variables,
and we have pre-specified them
to characterize different axes
by which we want to understand
the patient's disease
progression.
So in Thursday's
lecture, we characterized
the patient's disease as
subtype by just a single number,
and similarly in this example
is just by a single number,
but we might want to
understand what's really
unique about each subtype.
So for example--
sorry, what's really
unique about each disease stage.
So for example, how is the
patient's endocrine function
in that disease stage?
How is the patient's psychiatric
status in that disease stage?
Has the patient developed lung
cancer yet and that disease
stage?
And so on.
And so we're going
to ask that we
want to be able to read
out from this model
according to these
axes, and this
will become very clear at
the end of this section
where I show you a
simulation of what
20 years looks like for COPD
according to these quantities.
When does the patient
typically develop diabetes,
when does the patient
typically become depressed,
when does the patient typically
develop cancer, and so on.
So these are the
quantities in which
we want to be able
to really talk
about what happens to a patient
at any one disease stage,
but the challenge is, we
never actually observe
these quantities in
the data that we have.
Rather, all we observe are
things like laboratory test
results or diagnosis
codes or procedures
that have been formed
and so on, which
I'm going to call the clinical
findings in the bottom.
And as we've been discussing
throughout this course,
one could think about
things as diagnosis codes
as giving you information
about the disease
status of the patient,
but they're not
one and the same
as the diagnosis,
because there's so much
noise and bias that
goes into the assigning of
diagnosis codes for patients.
And so the way that we're
going to model the raw data
as a function of
these hidden variables
that we want to
characterize is using what's
known as a noisy-OR network.
So we're going to
suppose that there
is some generative distribution
where the observations you
see-- for example,
diagnosis codes
are likely to be observed as a
function of whether the patient
has these phenotypes
or comorbidities
with some probability, and that
probability can be specified
by these edge weights.
So for example, a
diagnosis code for diabetes
is very likely to be
observed in the patient data
if the patient
truly has diabetes,
but of course, it
may not be recorded
in the data for every
single visit the patient has
to a clinician, there
might be some visits
to clinicians that have nothing
to do with their patients
endocrine function and
diabetes-- the diagnosis
code might not be
recorded for that visit.
So it's going to
be a noisy process,
and that noise rate is going
to be captured by that edge.
So part of the
learning algorithm
is going to be to learn that
transition distributions--
for example, that Q matrix
I showed you in the earlier
slide, but the other
role-- learning algorithm
is to learn all
of the parameters
of this noisy-OR distribution,
namely these edge weights.
So that's going to be discovered
as part of the learning
algorithm.
And a key question
that you have to ask
me is, if I know I want
to read out from the model
according to these axes,
but these axes are never--
I'm never assuming
that they're explicitly
observed in the data, how
do I ground the learning
algorithm to give meaning
to these hidden variables?
Because otherwise if we left
them otherwise unconstrained
and you did maximum
likelihood estimation just
like in any factor
analysis-type model,
you might discover
some factors here,
but they might not be the
factors you care about,
and if the learning problem
was not identifiable,
as is often the case in
unsupervised learning,
then you might not discover
what you're interested in.
So to ground the
hidden variables,
we introduced-- we used a
technique that you already
saw in an earlier lecture
from lecture 8 called anchors.
So a domain expert
is going to specify
for each one of the comorbidites
one or more anchors, which
are observations, which
we are going to conjecture
could only have arisen from the
corresponding hidden variable.
So notice here
that this diagnosis
code, which is for
type 2 diabetes,
has only an edge from X1.
That is an assumption
that we're making
in the learning algorithm.
We are actually
explicitly zeroing
out all of the other edges from
all of the other comorbidities
to a 1.
We're not going to pre-specify
what this edge rate is,
we're going to allow for the
fact that this might be noisy,
it's not always observed even
if the patient has diabetes,
but we're going to
say, this could not
be explained by any of
the other comorbidities.
And so for each one of the
comorbidites or phenotypes
that we want to
model, we're going
to specify some small
number of anchors
which correspond to a type
of sparsity assumption
on that graph.
And these are the anchors
that we chose for asthma, we
chose a diagnosis code
corresponding to asthma;
for lung cancer, we
chose several diagnosis
codes correspond to lung
cancer; for obesity, we
chose a diagnosis
code corresponding
to morbid obesity; and so on.
And so these are
ways that we're going
to give meaning to
the hidden variables,
but as you'll see in
just a few minutes,
it is not going to pre-specify
too much of the model.
The model's still going
to learn a whole bunch
of other interesting things.
By the way, the way that we
actually came up with this set
was by an iterative process.
We specified some of the hidden
variables to have anchors,
but we also left some of
them to be unanchored,
meaning free variables.
We did our learning
algorithm, and just
like you would do
in a topic model,
we discovered that there
were some phenotypes that
really seemed to be
characterized by the patient's
disease--
that seemed to characterize a
patient's disease progression.
Then in order to really dig
deeper, working collaboratively
with a domain expert, we
specified anchors for those
and we iterated,
and in this way,
we discovered the full set
of interesting variables
that we wanted to model.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Did you measure how
good an anchor these were?
Like are some comorbidities
better anchors than others?
PROFESSOR: Great.
You'll see-- I think we'll
answer that question in just
a few minutes when I show
you what the graph looks
like that's learned.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Were all
the other weights
in that X to O network 0?
They weren't part of it here.
So it looks like
a pretty sparse--
PROFESSOR: They're
explicitly nonzero, actually,
it's opposite.
So for an anchor, we say that
it only has a single parent.
Everything that's
not an anchor can
have arbitrarily many parents.
Is that clear?
OK.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Do the anchors that
you have in that linear table,
you itereated yourself on
that or did the doctors say
that these are the [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: We started
out with just a subset
of these conditions.
As things that we
wanted to model--
things that we
wanted to understand
what happens along
disease progression
according to these axes,
but just a subset of them
originally.
And then we included a few
additional hidden variables
that didn't have any
anchors associated to them,
and after doing unsupervised
learning and just
a preliminary development stage,
they discovered some topics
and we realized, oh shoot,
we should have included those
in there, and then we added them
in with corresponding anchors.
And so you could think about
this as an exploratory data
analysis pipeline.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Is there a chance
that these aren't anchors?
PROFESSOR: Yes.
So there's definitely the
chance that these may not
be anchors related
to the question
was asked a second ago.
So for example, there
might be some chance
that the morbid
obesity diagnosis
code might be
coded for a patient
more often for a patient
who has, let's say, asthma--
this is a bad example.
And in which case, that would
correspond to there truly
existing an edge from
asthma to this anchor, which
would be a violation
of anchor assumption.
All right, so we chose
these to make that unlikely,
but it could happen.
And it's not easily testable.
So this is another example
of an untestable assumption,
just like we saw lots
of other examples
already in today's lecture and
the causal inference lectures.
If we had some ground
truth data-- like
if we had done chart review
for some number of patients
and we actually label
these conditions,
then we could test
that anchor assumption.
But here, we're assuming that we
don't actually know the ground
truth of these conditions.
AUDIENCE: Is there a
reason why you choose
such high-level comorbidites?
Like I imagine you
could go more specific.
Even, say, the
diabetes, you could
try to subtype the diabetes
based on this other model, sort
of use that as a single
layer, but it seems to--
at least this model seems to
choose [INAUDIBLE] high level.
I was just curious
of the reason.
PROFESSOR: Yes.
So that was a design
choice that we made.
There are many, many
directions for follow-up work,
one of which would be to use
a hierarchical model here.
But we hadn't gone
that direction.
Another obvious direction
for follow-up work
would be to do something within
the subtyping with this staging
by introducing another
random variable, which
is, let's say, the
disease subtype,
and making everything
a function of that.
OK, so I've talked
about the vertical slice
and I've talked about
the topmost slice,
but what I still need
to tell you about
is how these phenotypes relate
to the observed disease stage.
So for this, we use--
I don't remember the exact
technical terminology--
a factored Markov model?
Is that right, Pete?
Factorized Markov
model-- I mean,
this is a term that existed
in the graphical model's
literature, but I don't
remember right now.
So what we're saying is that
each of these Markov chains--
so each of these X1 up to Xt--
so this, will say, is the
first one I call diabetes.
This is the second one which
I'll say is depression.
We're going to assume that
each one of these Markov chains
is conditionally independent
of each other given the disease
stage.
So it's the disease stage
which ties everything together.
So the graphical model looks
like this, and so on, OK?
So in particular, there are
no edges between, let's say,
the diabetes variable and
the depression variable.
All correlations
between these conditions
is assumed to be mediated by
the disease stage variable.
And that's a critical
assumption that we had to make.
Does anyone know why?
What would go wrong if we
didn't make that assumption?
So for example,
what would go wrong
if we had something
look like this, x1--
what was my notation?
X1,1, X1,2, X1,3, and suppose
we had edges between them,
a complete graph, and
we had, let's say,
also the S variable with
edges to everything?
What would happen
in that case where
we're not assuming that the X's
are conditionally independent
given S?
So I want you to think about
this in terms of distributions.
So remember, we're
going to learn
how to do disease
progression through learning
the parameters of this model.
And so if we set this up and--
if we set up the learning
problem in a way which
is unidentifiable,
then we're going to
be screwed, we're
not going to able
to learn anything
about disease progression.
So what would happen
in this situation?
Someone who hasn't
spoken today ideally.
So any of you remember
from, let's say,
perhaps an earlier
machine learning
class what types
of distribution's
a complete graph--
a complete Bayesian
network could represent?
So the answer is
all distributions,
because it corresponds
to any factorization
of the joint distribution.
And so if you allowed
these x variables
to be fully connected to
each other-- so for example,
saying that depression depends
on diabetes in addition
to the stage, then in
fact, you don't even
need this stage
variable in here.
The marginal-- you can
fit any distribution
on these X variables even
without the S variable at all.
And so the model could
learn to simply ignore
the S variable, which would
be exactly not our goal,
because our goal is to learn
something about the disease
stage, and in fact,
we're going to be wanting
to make assumptions on
the progression of disease
stage, which is going
to help us learn.
So by assuming conditional
independence between these X
variables, it's going to
force all of the correlations
to have to be mediated
by that S variable,
and it's going to remove some
of that unidentifiability that
would otherwise exist.
It's this subtle but
very important point.
So the way that we're
going to parametrize
the conditional distribution--
so first of all,
I'm going to assume
these X's are all binary.
So either the
patient has diabetes
or they don't have diabetes.
I'm going to suppose that--
and this is, again, another
assumption we're making,
I'm going to suppose that once
you already have a comorbidity,
then you always have it.
So for example, once this is
1, then all subsequent ones
are also going to be 1.
Hold the questions
for just a second.
I'm also going to
make an assumption
that later stages of the disease
are more likely to develop
the comorbidity.
So in particular, one can
formalize that mathematically
as probability of X--
I'll just say Xi
being 1 given S--
I'll say St equals little
s, comma, Xt minus 1 equals
0, and suppose
that this is larger
than or equal to probability
of Xt equals 1 given St equals
S prime and Xt minus 1 equals
0 for all S prime less than S,
OK?
So I'm saying, as you get
further along in the disease
stage, you're more
likely to observe
one of these complications.
And again, this is an
assumption that we're
putting into the
learning algorithm,
but what we found that
these types of assumptions
are really critical in order
to learn disease progression
models when you don't have
a large amount of data.
And note that this is
just a linear inequality
on the parameters of the model.
And so one can use a convex
optimization algorithm
during learning--
during the maximum
likelihood estimation step
with this algorithm, we
just put a linear inequality
into the convex
optimization problem
to enforce this constraint.
There are a couple of questions.
AUDIENCE: Is there generally
like a quick way to check
whether a model is
unidentifiable or--
PROFESSOR: So there
are ways to try
to detect to see if a
model is unidentifiable.
It's beyond the
scope of the class,
but I'll just briefly mention
one of the techniques.
So one could-- so you can ask
the identifiability question
by looking at moments
of the distribution.
For example, you
could talk about it
as a function of
all of the observed
moments of distribution
that you get from the data.
Now the observed data here are
not the S's and X's, but rather
the O's.
So you look at the
joint distribution
on the O's, and then you
can ask questions about--
if I was to--
so suppose I was to choose
a random set of parameters
in the model, is
there any way to do
a perturbation of the
parameters in the model which
leave the observed marginal
distribution on the O's
identical?
And often when you're in the
setting of non-identifiability,
you can take the gradient
of a function and see--
and you could sort of find that
there is some wiggle space,
and then you show that
OK, there are actually--
this objective function is
actually unidentifiable.
Now that type of
technique is widely
used when studying what are
known as method of moments
algorithms or
estimation algorithms
in learning verbal models,
but they would be much, much
harder to apply in this type of
setting because first of all,
these are much more
complex models,
and estimating the
corresponding moments
is going to be very hard because
they're very high dimensional.
And second, because they're--
I'm actually conflating
two different things when
I talk about identifiability.
One statement is the infinite
data identifiability,
and the second question
is your ability
to actually learn a good model
from a small amount of data,
which is a sample complexity.
And these constraints
that I'm putting in,
even if they don't affect
the actual identifiability
of the model, they
could be extremely
important for improving the
sample complexity of learning
algorithm.
Is there another question?
So we valued to
this using a data
set of almost 4,000
patients where,
again, each patient we observed
for only a couple of years--
one to three years.
And the observations
that we observed
were 264 diagnosis
codes, the presence
or absence of each of
those diagnosis codes
during any three-month interval.
Overall, there were almost
200,000 observations
of diagnosis codes
in this data set.
The learning
algorithm that we used
was expectation maximization.
Remember, there are a number
of hidden variables here,
and so if you want to
maximize the likely--
if you want to learn the
parameters that maximize
the likelihood of
those observations O,
then you have to marginize
over those hidden variables,
and EM is one way to try to
find a local optima of that
likelihood function, with the
key caveat that one has to do
approximate inference
during the E step here,
because this model
is not tractable,
there's no closed form--
for example, dynamic programming
algorithm for doing posterior
inference in this model
given its complexity.
And so what we used
was a Gibbs sampler
to do approximate inference
within that E step,
and we used--
we did block sampling
of the Markov chains
where we combined
a Gibbs sampler
with a dynamic programming
algorithm, which
improved the mixing
rate of the Markov chain
for those of you who are
familiar with those concepts.
And in the end step of the
learning algorithm when
one has to learn the
parameters of the distribution,
the only complex
part of this model
is the continuous
time Markov process,
and there's actually
been previous literature
from the physics community
which shows how you can really--
which gives you analytic
closed-form solutions
for that M step of that
continuous time Markov process.
Now if I were to do
this again today,
I would have done it a
little bit differently.
I would still think about
modeling this problem
in a very similar
way, but I would
do learning using a
variational lower bound
of the likelihood with
a recognition network
in order to very quickly
get you a lower bound
in the likelihood.
And for those of
you who are familiar
with variational
autoencoders, that's
precisely the idea
that is used there
for learning variational
autoencoders.
So that's the way I
would approach this
if I was to do it again.
There's just one or two other
extensions I want to mention.
The first one is
something which we--
one, more customization
we made for COPD,
which is that we enforced
monotonic stage progression.
So we said that--
so here I talked about
a type of monotonically
in terms of the conditional
distribution of X
given S, but one could also
put an assumption in the--
I already talked about
that, but one could also
put an assumption on P of S--
S of t given S of t minus
1, which is implicitly
an assumption on
Q, and I gave you
a hint of how one might
do that over here when
I said that you might put 0's to
the left-hand side, meaning you
can never go to the left.
And indeed, we did
something like that
here as well, which is
another type of constraint.
And finally, we regularize
the learning problem
by asking about
that graph involving
the conditions,
the comorbidities,
and the diagnosis
codes be sparse,
by putting a beta prior
on those edge weights.
So here's what one learned.
So the first thing
I'm going to do
is I'm going to show you the--
we talked about how
we specified anchors,
but I told you that the anchors
weren't the whole story.
That we were able to infer
much more interesting things
about the hidden variables
given all of the observations
we have.
So here I'm showing you
several of the phenotypes that
were learned by this
unsupervised learning
algorithm.
First, the phenotype
for kidney disease.
In red here, I'm showing
you the anchor variables
that we chose for kidney
disease, and what you'll notice
are a couple of things.
First, the weight, which
you should think about
as being proportional
in some way
to how often you would see
that diagnosis code given
that the patient
had kidney disease,
the weights are all far
less than one, all right?
So there is some noise in this
process of when you observe
a diagnosis code for a patient.
The second thing you
observe is that there
are a number of other diagnosis
codes that are observed to be--
which are explained by this
kidney disease comorbidity,
such as anemia, urinary
tract infections, and so on,
and that aligns well with what's
known in the medical literature
about kidney disease.
Look at another example
for lung cancer.
In red here I'm
showing you the anchors
that we had pre-specified
for these, which
mean that these diagnosis
codes could only be explained
by the lung cancer
comorbidity, and these
are the noise rates that
are learned for them,
and that's everything else.
And here's one more
example of lung infection
where there was only a signal
anchor that we specified
for pneumonia, and you see
all of the other things that
are automatically
associated to that as
by the unsupervised
learning algorithm.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: So how
do you [INAUDIBLE]
for the mobidity, right?
PROFESSOR: Right.
So that's what the unsupervised
learning algorithm is doing.
So these weights are
learned, and I'm showing you
something like a point
estimate of the parameters
that are learned by
the learning algorithm.
AUDIENCE: And so we--
PROFESSOR: Just like if you're
learning a Markov model,
you learned some transition and
[INAUDIBLE],, same thing here.
All right.
And this should
look a lot like what
you would see when you do topic
modeling on a text copora,
right?
You would discover a topic--
this is analogous to a topic.
It's a discrete topic,
meaning it either occurs
or it doesn't occur
for a patient.
And you would discover some
word topic distribution.
This is analogous to that
word topic distribution
for a topic in a topic model.
So one could then use
the model to answer
a couple of the original
questions we set out to solve.
The first one is given
a patient's data,
which I'm illustrating
here on the bottom,
I have artificially
separated out
into three different
comorbidities,
and a star denotes
an observation
of a data type of that one.
But this was
artificially done by us,
it was not given to
learning algorithm.
One can infer, when
the patient initiated--
started with each one of these
comorbidites, and also, when--
so for the full
three-year time range
that we have data
for the patient, what
stage was the patient in
in the disease at any one
point in time?
So this model infers that the
patient starts out in stage 1,
and about half a year
through the data collection
process, transitioned
into stage 2 of COPD.
Another thing that one
could do using this model
is to simulate from the model
and answer the question of what
would, let's say, a 20-year
trajectory of the disease look
like?
And here, I'm showing
a 10-year trajectory.
And again, only one
to three years of data
was used for any one
patient during learning.
So this is the first time
we see the those axes,
those comorbidities
really start to show up
as being important as the way
of reading out from the model.
Here, we've thrown away those
O's, those diagnosis codes
altogether, we only care about
what we conjecture is truly
happening to the patient,
those X variables, which
are unobserved during training.
So what we conjecture is that
kidney disease is very uncommon
in stage 1 of the disease,
and increases slowly as you
transition from stage 2, stage
3, to stage 4 of the disease,
and then really bumps
up towards stage 5
and stage 6 of the disease.
So you should read
this as saying
that in stage 6 of
the disease, over 60%
people have kidney disease.
Now the time interval is here.
So how I've chosen these--
where to put these
triangles, I've
chosen them based on the
average amount of time
it takes to transition from
one stage to the next stage
according to the learned
parameters of the model.
And so you see that
stages 1, 2, and 3,
and 4 take a long period of--
amount of time to transition
between those four stages,
and then there's a
very small amount
of time between
transitioning from stage 5
to stage 6 on average.
So that's for kidney disease.
One could also read this
out for other comorbidities.
So in orange here--
in yellow here
is diabetes, in black here is
musculoskeletal conditions,
and in red here is
cardiovascular disease.
And so one of the
interesting inferences
made by this
learning algorithm is
that even in stage 1 of COPD,
very early in the trajectory,
we are seeing patients
with large amounts
of cardiovascular disease.
And again, this is
something that one
can look at the
medical literature
to see does it align
with what we expect?
And it does, so even in patients
with mild to moderate COPD,
the leading cause of morbidity
is cardiovascular disease.
Again, this is
just a sanity check
that what this model is learning
for a common disease actually
aligns with the
medical knowledge.
So that's all I want to say
about this probabilistic model
approach to disease
progression modeling
from cross-sectional data.
I want you to hold
your questions
so I can get through
the rest of the material
and you can ask me after class.
So next I want to talk about
these pseudo-time methods,
which are a very different
approach for trying
to align patients into
early-to-late disease stage.
These approaches were really
popularized in the last five
years due to the explosion
in single-cell sequencing
experiments in the
biology community.
Single-cell sequencing is
a way to really understand
not just what is the
average gene expression,
but on a cell-by-cell
basis can we
understand what is
expressed in each cell.
So at a very high level,
the way this works is
you take a solid tissue, you
do a number of procedures
in order to isolate
out individual cells
from that tissue,
then you're going
to extract the RNA from
those individual cells,
you go through another
complex procedure
which somehow barcodes
each of the RNA
from each individual cell,
mixes them all together,
does sequencing of it,
and then deconvolves
it so that you can see
what was the original RNA
expression for each of
the individual cells.
Now the goal of these
pseudo-time algorithms
is to take that type
of data and then
to attempt to align
cells to some trajectory.
So if you look at the very
top of this figure part figure
a that's the picture that
you should have in your mind.
In the real world, cells
are evolving with time--
for example, B cells will have
a well-characterized evolution
between different
cellular states,
and what we'd like
to be understand,
given that you have
cross-sectional data-- so you
can imagine-- imagine you have
a whole collection of cells,
each one in a different
part, a different stage
of differentiation,
could you somehow
order them into where they
were in different stages
of differentiation?
So that's the goal.
We want to take this--
so there exists some
true ordering that I'm
showing from dark to light.
The capture process
is going to ignore
what the ordering information
was, because all we're doing
is getting a collection of cells
that are in different stages.
And then we're going to
use this pseudo-time method
to try to re-sort them so
that you could figure out,
oh, these were the
cells in the early stage
and these are the cells
in the late stage.
And of course,
there's an analogy
here to the pictures I
showed you in the earlier
part of the lecture.
Once you have this alignment
of cells into stages,
then you can answer some really
exciting scientific questions.
For example, you could ask
a variety of different genes
which genes are expressed
at which point in time.
So you might see that
gene a is very highly
expressed very early in
this cell's differentiation
and is not expressed very
much towards the end,
and that might give you
new biological insights.
So these methods
could immediately
be applied, I believe, to
disease progression modeling
where I want you to think about
each cell as now a patient,
and that patient has a number
of observations for this data.
The observations are an
expression for that cell,
but in our data,
the observations
might be symptoms that we
observe for the patient,
for example.
And then the goal is,
given those cross-sectional
observations, to sort them.
And once you have
that sorting, then you
could answer
scientific questions,
such as, I mentioned, of a
number of different genes,
which genes are expressed when.
So here, I'm showing you
sort of the density of when
this particular
gene is expressed
as a function of pseudo-time.
Analogously for disease
progression modeling,
you should think of
that as being a symptom.
You could ask, OK, suppose
there are some true progression
of the disease, when do patients
typically develop diabetes
or cardiovascular symptoms?
And so for cardiovascular,
going back to the COPD example,
you might imagine that there's
a peak very early in the disease
stage; for diabetes, it might
be in a later disease stage.
All right?
So that-- is the analogy clear?
So this community, which
has been developing methods
for studying single-cell
gene expression data,
has just exploded in
the last 10 years.
So I lost count of how many
different methods there
are, but if I had to guess, I'd
say 50 to 200 different methods
for this problem.
There was a paper, which is
one of the optional readings
for today's lecture, that just
came out earlier this month
which looks at a comparison
of these different trajectory
inference methods,
and this picture
gives a really
interesting illustration
of what are some of
the assumptions made
by these algorithms.
So for example,
the first question,
when you try to figure out which
method of these tons of methods
to use is, do you expect
multiple disconnected
trajectories?
What might be a reason
why you would expect
multiple disconnected
trajectories for disease
progression modeling?
TAs should not answer.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Different
subtexts would be an example.
So suppose the answer
is no, as we've
been assuming for most of this
lecture, then you might ask,
OK, there might only be a single
trajectory, because we're only
assuming that a single
disease subtype,
but do we expect a
particular topology?
Now everything that we've been
talking about up until now
has been a linear
topology, meaning
there's a linear
projection, there's
such notion of early
and late to stage,
but in fact, the
linear trajectory
may not be realistic.
Maybe the trajectory
looks a little bit more
like this bifurcation.
Maybe patients look the same
very early in the disease
stage, but then
suddenly something
might happen which causes
some patients to go
this way and some
patients to go that way.
Any idea what that might
be in a clinical setting?
AUDIENCE: A treatment?
PROFESSOR: Treatments,
that's great.
All right?
So maybe these patients
got t equals 0,
and maybe these patients
got t equal as 1, and maybe
for whatever reason
wouldn't even
have good data on what
treatments patients got,
so we don't actually observe
the treatment, right?
Then you might want to be able
to discover that bifurcation
directly from the data, then
that might suggest, going back
to the original source
of the data, to ask,
what differentiated these
patients at this point in time?
And you might
discover, oh, there
was something in the data
that we didn't record,
such as treatment, all right?
So there are a
variety of methods
to try to infer these
pseudo-times under a variety
of different assumptions.
What I'll do in the
next few minutes
is just give you an inkling of
how two of the methods work.
And I chose these to be
representative examples.
The first example
is an approach based
on building a minimum
spanning tree.
And this algorithm
I'm going to describe
goes by the name of Monocle.
It was published in 2014 in
this paper by Trapnell et al,
but it builds very heavily
on an earlier published
paper from 2003 that
I mostly citing here.
So the way that this
algorithm works is as follows.
It starts with, as
we've been assuming
all along, cross-sectional
data, which lives
in some high-dimensional space.
I'm drawing that in
the top-left here.
Each data point corresponds
to some patient or some cell.
The first step of
the algorithm is
to do dimensionality reduction.
And there are many ways to
do dimensionality reduction.
You could do principal
components analysis,
or, for example, you could
do independent components
analysis.
This paper uses the
independent component analysis.
What ICA is going
to do, it's going
to attempt to find a number
of different components that
seem to be as independent
from one another as possible.
Then you're going to
represent the data now
in this low-dimensional space,
and in many of these papers,
it's quite astonishing to me,
they actually use dimension 2.
So they'll go all the way
down to two-dimensional space
where you can actually
plot all of the data.
It's not at all obvious to me
why you would want to do that,
and for clinical data,
I think that might
be a very poor choice.
Then what they do is they build
a minimum spanning tree on all
of the patient or cells.
So the way that one
does that is you
create a graph by drawing
an edge between every pair
of nodes where the
weight of the edge
is the Euclidean distance
between those two points.
And then-- so for example, there
is this edge from here to here,
there's an edge from
here to here and so on.
And then given that
weighted graph,
we're going to find the minimum
spanning tree of that graph,
and what I'm showing you here
is the minimum spanning tree
of the corresponding graph, OK?
Next, what one
will do is go look
for the longest
path in that tree.
Remember, finding the
longest path in a graph--
in an arbitrary
graph has a name,
it's called the traveling
salesman problem
and it's the NP-hard problem.
How has that gotten around here?
Well we're not-- this is
not an arbitrary graph,
this is actually a tree.
So here's that poor--
here's a algorithm for
finding the longest path.
I won't talk about that.
So one finds along
this path in a tree--
in the tree, and then
what one does is one says,
OK, one side of the
path corresponds to,
let's say, early disease stage
and the other side of the path
corresponds to
late disease stage,
and it allows for
the fact that there
might be some bifurcation.
So for example, you
see here that there
is a bifurcation over here.
And as we discussed
earlier, you have
to have some way
of differentiating
what the beginning is and
what the end should be,
and that's where some side
information might become
useful.
So here's an illustration
of applying that method
to some real data.
So every point here
is a cell after doing
dimensionality reduction.
The edges between
those points correspond
to the edges of the
minimum spanning tree,
and now what the
authors have done
is they've actually used some
side information that they
had in order to color
each of the nodes
based on what part of the
cell differentiation process
is believed-- that cell
is believed to be in.
And what one discovers,
that in fact, this
is very sensible, that
all of these points
are in a much
earlier disease stage
than [INAUDIBLE]
than these points,
and this is a
sensible bifurcation
Next I want to talk about a
slightly different approach
to--
this is the whole story,
by the way, right?
It's conceptually a very,
very simple approach.
Next I want to talk about
a different approach, which
now tries to return back to
the probabilistic approaches
that we had earlier
in the lecture.
This new approach is going to
be based on Gaussian processes.
So Gaussian processes have
come up a couple of times
in lecture, but
I've never actually
formally defined them for you.
So in order for what I'm going
to say next to make sense,
I'm going to formally define for
you what a Gaussian process is.
A Gaussian process mu for a
collection of time points,
T1 through T capital
N, is defined
by a joint distribution,
mu, of those time points,
which is a Gaussian
distribution.
So we're going to
say that the function
value for these T different
time points is just
a Gaussian, which for the
purpose of today's lecture
I'm going to assume
is zero mean,
and where the covariance
function is given
to you by this capital K, it's a
covariance function of the time
points-- of the input points.
And so if you look--
this has to be a matrix
of dimension capital N
by capital N. And if you look
at the I1 and I2 of the N tree,
if you look at the N
tree of that matrix,
we're defining it to be given
to by the following kernel
function.
It looks at the exponential
of the negative Euclidean
distance squared between
those two time points.
Intuitively what
this is saying is
that if you have
two time points that
are very close to
one another, then
this kernel function is
going to be very large.
If you have two time points that
are very far from one another,
then this is very large-- it's
a very large negative number,
and so this is going
to be very small.
So the kernel function
for two inputs that
are very far from
another are very small;
the kernel function
for inputs that
are very close to
each other is large;
and thus, what
we're saying here is
that there's going to be some
correlation between nearby data
points.
And that's the way which
we're going to specify
a distribution of functions.
If one were to sample
from this Gaussian
with a covariance function
specified in the way I did,
what one gets out is something
that looks like this.
So I'm assuming
here that every--
that these curves
look really dense,
and that's because I'm assuming
the N is extremely large here.
If and what small, let's
say 3, there'd only
be three time points here, OK?
And so if you can make this
distribution of functions
be arbitrarily complex by
playing with this little l--
so for example, if you made
a little l be very small,
then what you get are these
really spiky functions
that I'm showing you
in a very light color.
If you make a little
l be very large,
you get these very
smooth functions, right?
So this is a way to get a
function-- this is a way
to get a distribution
over functions
just by sampling from
this Gaussian process.
What this paper does from
Campbell and Yau published
two years ago in
Computational Biology
is they assume that the
observations that you have
are drawn from a Gaussian
distribution whose mean is
given to you by the
Gaussian process.
So if you think back to the
story that we drew earlier,
suppose that the data lived
in just one dimension,
and suppose we actually knew
the sorting of patients.
So we actually
knew which patients
are very early in time, which
patients are very late in time.
You might imagine that that
single biomarker, biomarker A,
you might imagine that the
function which tells you
what the biomarker's value
is as a function of time
might be something
like this, right?
Or maybe it's something
like that, OK?
So it might be a function
that's increasing
or a function that's decreasing.
And this function
is precisely what
this mu, this Gaussian
process is meant to model.
The only difference is that
now, one can model the Gaussian
process-- instead of just
being a single dimension,
one could imagine having
several different dimensions.
So this P denotes the
number of dimensions, right?
Which corresponds
to, in some sense,
to the number of
synthetic biomarkers
that you might conjecture exist.
Now here, we truly don't
know the sorting of patients
into early versus late stage.
And so the time points
T are themselves
assumed to be latent
variables that
are drawn from a truncated
normal distribution that
looks like this.
So you might make
some assumption
that the time intervals
for when a patient comes in
might be, maybe patients
come in really typically very
in the middle of
the disease stage,
or maybe you're assuming
it's something flat,
an so patients come in
throughout the disease stage.
But the time point
itself is latent.
So now the generative process
for the data is as follows.
You first sample
a time point from
this truncated normal
distribution, then
you look to see--
oh, and you sample
from the very beginning
your sample this
curve mu, and then you
look to see, what is the value
of mu for the sample time
point, and that gives you
the expected value you should
expect to see for that patient.
And the one, then,
jointly optimizes
this to try to find the most--
the curve, the curve mu
which has highest posterior
probability, and that is how
you read out from the model
both what the latent
progression looks
like, and if you look at
the posterior distribution
over the T's that are
inferred for each individual,
you get the inferred
location along the trajectory
for each individual.
And I'll stop there.
I'll post the slides
online for this last piece,
but I'll let you read
the paper on your own.